Guide to the Jon Charles Acker Collection of Religious Certificates 1845-1942 PR 360
New-York Historical Society
Jon Charles Acker collection of religious certificates
1845-1942
New-York Historical Society
Acker, Jon Charles
PR 360
2 Linear feet in one flat box
The collection includes certificates documenting marriages (58), baptisms (8), confirmations (7), and deaths (3), primarily from New York State. Most are from the 19th century and are of a religious nature, with many depicting Christian imagery and text. Some certificates are in German.
Related Archival Materials Note
New-York Historical Society holds a large variety of certificates compiled over time in its Certificates File collection. Among the many types of certificates found there are those of a "legal" nature, including those for marriages, births, deaths, etc.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
Gift of Jon Charles Acker, February 2018.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Biographical/Historical Note
Jon Charles Acker, Ph.D., began collecting religious ephemera about 2008, obtaining thousands over time. His principal purpose was to preserve the documents, keeping a digital copy for himself then donating or selling the original to an appropriate institutional or other collection, typically one open to public access. His collecting focus was on baptismal forms, particularly in the Pennsylvania Dutch tradition, though he also sought marriage, confirmation, communion, and other religious forms, all generally dating from before 1930. The collection held by New-York Historical Society represents just some of Acker's acquisitions, that is, certificates related to New York State.
(The above note is based on information provided by Dr. Acker in an email to N-YHS curator Marilyn Kushner.)
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged by type of certificate and then chronological within type.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes certificates documenting marriages (58), baptisms (8), confirmations (7), and deaths (3). The bulk are of a religious nature, with many depicting Christian imagery and text. The bulk are from events that occurred in New York State, with a small number concerning out of state events that involved someone from New York (e.g., a groom from New York marrying in his bride's out of state hometown). The bulk are from the 19th century, with a few from the early 20th century. Some of the marriage certificates are of a form that allowed for the insertion of cartes-de-visite of the bride and groom; the container list identifies where such photographs are included. Some of the certificates are in German and these are also noted in the container list. All documents in the collection are identified to the item level in the container list.
Marriage certificates.; New York (State); Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Ephemera.; Religious visual works.; Baptismal certificates.
- Marriage. Minden (?), NY. Peter H. House & Nancy Lighthall, 1845 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York, NY. James Morris & Janet Whitehill, 1848(?) (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Clarksville, NY. Isaac Noscort & Sophia Simons, 1850 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Brooklyn, NY. George N. Yerks & Mary G. Marquys, 1851 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York State. William Tripp & Mary Janette Rowe, 1851 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York State. John Nesbit & Sarah Anne Matthews, 1851 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Rochester, NY. Sylvester P. Atwood & Susan W. Moulton, 1856 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York (?). James H. Merrill & Louisa W. Reed, 1856 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Ovid, NY. Alva Bogardus & Angeline Patterson, 1857 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York (?), NY. Norman S. Edgerly & Marye Gibb, 1858 (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Backing of marriage certificate includes a crayon drawing.
- Marriage. New York State. John Sterling & Unice B. Saltin (?), 1861 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York, NY. Bernando Borzone & Johanna Spilberg, 1863 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Hampton, NY. Alexander L. Frenette & Frances L. Harrison, 1864 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Constable, NY. Franklin N. Graves & Mary E. Vania, 1864 (Offsite-box 1)
  Marriage certificate includes envelope addressed to Mary E. Graves from the Department of the Interior, Bureau of Pensions.
- Marriage. Sauquoit, NY. Erastus Congden & Sarah Stedman, 1864 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. East Schuyler, NY. Joseph J. Dudleston & Hattie N. Smith, 1865 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Hornby, NY. James Leak & Mary S. Newman, 1865 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Neversink, NY. Ezra Bliss & Roana Vandervort, 1866 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Chenango, NY. Larry D. Booth & Julia O. Thomas, 1866 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Raymondville, NY. George G. Sheets & Frances Hellen Bishop, 1868 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Middle Island, NY. George C. Marshall & Sarah Ellen Field, 1868 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Pennsylvania. George Elliot (of New York) & Anna S. Wallace, 1869 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York State. Miners Perry & Jennette Barnes, 1869 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York State. Martin Helfer & Sarah E Ehyle (?), 1872 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Canastota, NY. Samuel H. McKee & Laura L. Keeney, 1873 (Offsite-box 1)
  Marriage certificate includes carte-de-visite of the bride.
- Marriage. New York State. William H. Cornue & Almeda Long, 1874 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Norwich, NY. Henry Packard & Rosa A. Beale, 1875(?) (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Brookfield, NY. Edwin Granger & Lillian Dye, 1877 (Offsite-box 1)
  Marriage certificate includes cartes-de-visite of bride and groom.
- Marriage. Baldwins, NY. Pettit Smith & Payne Jola (?), 1877 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Fredonia, NY. Oliver Markham & Amanda Wakely (?), 1879 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York(?). William H. Nesbit & Leonore H. Cleveland, 1880 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Saugerties, NY. Girden R. Smith & Libbie Montross, 1880 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Syracuse, NY. James Dean & Adelia Coon, 1881 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Niagra County, NY. Johan Georg Kuch & Anna Jacobs, 1881 (Offsite-box 1)
  Packet includes a portrait photograph of a gentleman in a coat and tie.
- Marriage. Brooklyn, NY (?). Franz G. Goertz & Wilhelmina Gurner (?), 1882 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Fort Plain, NY. Charles Leneker & Mary Bote, 1883 (Offsite-box 1)
  Marriage certificate includes cartes-de-visite of the bride and groom.
- Marriage. Brooklyn, NY. Edward Johnson & Selena Alida Person, 1883 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York, NY. (First name?) Gustave Miller & Katie Meyers. In German, 1884 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York State. James Charles & Annie M. Helter, 1884 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Green River, NY. Durton M. Murphy & Ann Maria Tremper(?), 1884(?) (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Syracuse, NY. Frank Bohner & Rosa Miller, 1886 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Forestburgh, NY. James W. White & Mary E. Stanton, 1886 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Brooklyn, NY. Arthur John Smith & Eva Bell Yerks, 1888 (Offsite-box 1)
  Packet of documents also includes a marriage certificate for George Smith & Harriett S. Marquis (Brooklyn, NY., 1890); a 1903 Brooklyn receipt from Mr. Smith to George G. Englert (boarding and livery stable business) for embalming and other burial-related services; a 1903 Cypress Hills Cemetery receipt for the interment of Harriet Smith, aged 58, in lot 236, section 4; a 1896 program for memorial services of the Grand Army of the Republic at Cypress Hills Cemetery; and a 1898 program for memorial services at the grave of Col. James H. Perry of the 48th Regiment, New York State Volunteers.
- Marriage. Sand Lake, NY. George W. Conant & Elizabeth Wainman, 1888 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Scio, NY. Frank Palmer & Inez P. Clark, 1890 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. New York, NY. Charles Graebner & Christine Broefel (?). In German, 1890 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Knowlesville, NY. Milton W. Johnson & Hattie Hyde, 1892 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Jamestown, NY. Adolph Bartholme & Bertha Blakslee, 1892 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Syracuse. William D. Thompcon & Louise M. Coucer (?), 1893 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Buffalo, NY. William J. King & Ida L. Eccles, 1893 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Ithaca, NY. Charles Y. Rockwell & Anna Parry, 1899 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Unidentified Photograph, circa 1900? (Offsite-box 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes an 11x14 photograph of a bride and groom. Found in collection with a paper clip attached to it, but no other attached documents. Possibly related to one of the certificates, but unidentifiable.
- Marriage. Lowville, NY. Frank G. Van Namee & Ollie O. Gardner, 1902 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Waterbury, CT. Caspar Richter (of Brooklyn) & Bessie Sestle (?), 1905 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Nassau, NY. Stanley Lydecker & Frances Van Valkenburg, 1907 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Rochester, NY. John F. Friesmann & Martha Selke, 1913 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Rochester, NY. William Edmund Krautwurst & Matilda Jungjohann, 1915 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Colchester, VT. Oliver Gauvreau (of Brooklyn) & Viola E. Potter, 1917 (Offsite-box 1)
- Marriage. Stuyvesant, NY. Raymond D. Morris & Hannie B. Dalkins, 1921 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Brooklyn, NY. Georg Peter Schlatterer (Peter Schlatterer & Catharine Wittmann). In German, 1874 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Plato, NY. Wilhelm Reinhold Gonne Hinz (?) (Albert Richard Hinz & Josephine Maria Prill). In German, 1902 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Brooklyn, NY. Sally Carolina Margareta Fredholm (Oscar A. Fredholm & Sally C. Fredholm), 1906 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Lyons, NY. Bernice Elizabeth Walter (Albert Philip Walter & Elizabeth Walter), 1911 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Lyons, NY. Philip Albert Walter (Albert Philip Walter & Elizabeth Walter), 1911 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Throgg's Neck, NY. Herbert Charles Reichert (William Nelson Reichert & Wilhelmina Rogers Reichert), 1926 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Saugerties, NY. Janet Florence Neiffer (Augustus Neiffer & Rachel Nish Neiffer), 1930 (Offsite-box 1)
- Baptism. Baldwin, NY. Margaret Verity Jackson (Harry Verity & Anna Rohrer), 1942 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. East New York, NY. Caspar Richter. In German, 1879 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Brooklyn, NY. Annie Gussie Birkle, 1898 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Saugerties, NY. Ella Elisabeth Krieger, 1898 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Tremont, NY. Sadie Viola Miller. In German, 1908 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Jersey City, NJ. Sarah Josephine Riche, 1913 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Buffalo, NY. Marjory A. Osborne, 1924 (Offsite-box 1)
- Confirmation. Buffalo, NY. Jack William Hauenstein, 1935 (Offsite-box 1)
- Death. Hamlin, NY. Georg Johann Franz Kleinbach. In German, 1888 (Offsite-box 1)
- Death. Hamlin, NY. Catharine Caroline Sophie Kleinbach. In German, 1893 (Offsite-box 1)
- Death. Hamlin, NY. Ernst Richard Wilhelm Kleinbach. In German, 1893 (Offsite-box 1)